<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<article version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>WebDyne Installation and Usage Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Andrew</firstname><surname>Speer</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <address><email>andrew@webdyne.org</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2026</year>

      <holder role="mailto:andrew.speer@isolutions.com.au">Andrew Speer</holder>
    </copyright>
  </info>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Introduction</title>
    </info>

    <para>WebDyne is a Perl based dynamic HTML engine. It works with web servers (or from the command line) to render HTML documents with embedded Perl code.</para>

    <para>Once WebDyne is installed and initialised any file with a <filename>.psp</filename> extension is treated as a WebDyne source file. It is parsed for WebDyne pseudo-tags (such as
    <markup>&lt;perl&gt;</markup> and <markup>&lt;block&gt;</markup>) which are interpreted and executed on the server. The resulting output is then sent to the browser.</para>

    <para>WebDyne works with common web server persistent Perl interpreters - such as Apache <command>mod_perl</command> and <command>PSGI</command> - to provide fast dynamic content. It works
    with PSGI servers such as Plack and <productname>Starman</productname>, and can be implemented as a Docker container to run HTML with embedded Perl code.</para>

    <para>Pages are parsed once, then stored in a partially compiled format - speeding up subsequent processing by avoiding the need to re-parse a page each time it is loaded.</para>

    <para>Alternate syntaxes are available to enable WebDyne code to be used with editors that do not recognise custom HTML tags, and the syntax supports the use of PHP type processing
    instruction tags (<markup>&lt;?..?&gt;</markup>) or <markup>&lt;div&gt;</markup> tags (via data attributes such as <markup>&lt;div data-webdyne-perl&gt;</markup>) to define WebDyne
    blocks.</para>

    <para>Perl code can be co-mingled in the HTML code for "quick and dirty" pages or completed isolated into separate files or modules for separation of presentation and logic layers. You can
    see examples in a dedicated section - but here are a few very simple examples as an overview.</para>

    <para>Simple HTML file with Perl code embedded using WebDyne :</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction1.psp" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>This can be abbreviated with some WebDyne shortcut tags such as <markup>&lt;start_html&gt;</markup>. This does exactly the same thing and still renders compliant HTML to the
    browser:</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Don't like the co-mingling code and HTML but still want things in one file ?</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Want further code and HTML separation ? You can import methods from any external Perl module. Example from a core module below, but could be any installed CPAN module or your own
    code:</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Same concepts implemented in slightly different ways:</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction6.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction6.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Using an editor that doesn't like custom tags ? Use of the <tag>&lt;div&gt;</tag> tag with a <literal>data-*</literal> attribute is legal HTML syntax and can be used to embed
    Perl:</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction7.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction7.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Don't like <tag>&lt;div&gt;</tag> style syntax ? Put the code in a <tag>&lt;script&gt;</tag> block - it will be interpreted on the server, not the client:</para>

    <para><example>
        <info>
          <title>Basic Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction8.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction7.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Template blocks and variable replacement is supported also:</para>

    <example>
      <info>
        <title>Template Example</title>
      </info>

      <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/introduction9.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
      xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/introduction9.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Installation and Quickstart</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <para>WebDyne will install and run on any modern Linux system that has a recent version of Perl installed and is capable of installing Perl module via CPAN. Installation via Docker is
      also supported.</para>

      <para>When installing WebDyne there are two components which are required before you can begin serving .psp files:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The core WebDyne Perl modules</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A web server configured to use WebDyne</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>WebDyne will work with Apache mod_perl or PSGI compatible web servers (such as Plack, Starman etc.).</para>

      <para>Docker containers with pre-built versions of WebDyne are also available.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing via CPAN or CPANMinus</title>

      <para>Install from the Perl CPAN library using <command>cpan</command> or <command>cpanm</command> utilities. Installs dependencies if required (also from CPAN).</para>

      <para>Destination of the installed files is dependent on the local CPAN configuration, however in most cases it will be to the Perl site library location. WebDyne supports installation
      to an alternate location using the PREFIX option in CPAN. Binaries are usually installed to <filename>/usr/bin</filename> or <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename> by CPAN, but may vary by
      distribution/local configuration.</para>

      <para>Assuming your CPAN environment is setup correctly you can run the command:</para>

      <para><command>perl -MCPAN -e "install WebDyne"</command></para>

      <para>Or (with <command>cpanminus</command> if installed)</para>

      <para><command>cpanm WebDyne</command></para>

      <para>This will install the base WebDyne modules, which includes the Apache config utility and PSGI version. Note that Apache or PSGI servers and dependencies such as Plack or Starman
      are <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> installed by default and need to be installed separately - see the relevant section.</para>

      <para>Once installed you will need to configure your web server to use WebDyne to serve files with the <filename>.psp</filename> extension if using Apache - see section below.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quickstart</title>

      <para>If using PSGI you can start a quick web server by creating a simple app.psp file:</para>

      <programlisting>#  Save this as app.psp
#
&lt;start_html&gt;
My first WebDyne page. Server time: &lt;? localtime ?&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Then test install:</para>

      <para><screen language="bash">#  Render the file to STDOUT to see the HTML and check basic installation
#
$ <command>wdrender app.psp</command>

#  Install Plack and some Plack Middleware
#
$ <command>cpanm Plack</command>
$ <command>cpanm Plack::Middleware::ForceEnv</command>

#  Check all working
#
$ <command>webdyne.psgi --test</command>

#  Start serving only a single PSP file
#
$ <command>webdyne.psgi app.psp</command>

# Start serving any file in the current directory. If app.psp exists it will be served by
# default, otherwise an index page will be presented
#
$ <command>webdyne.psgi .</command>

# Start but listen on non-default port, only on localhost
#
$ <command>webdyne.psgi --port=5001 --host=127.0.0.1</command></screen>Connect your browser to the host and you should see the WebDyne output</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Apache mod_perl</title>

      <para>If using Apache with mod_perl you can initialise WebDyne using the <command>wdapacheinit</command> command. This will attempt to auto-discover where the Apache binary and
      configuration files are, then add a suitable <filename>webdyne.conf</filename> file to the apache configuration. Apache will need to be restarted for the new configuration file to take
      effect. This will need to be done as a the root user.</para>

      <para><screen language="bash">[root@localhost ~]# <command>wdapacheinit</command> 

[install] - Installation source directory '/usr'.
[install] - Creating cache directory '/var/cache/webdyne'.

[install] - Writing Apache config file '/etc/httpd/conf.d/webdyne.conf'.
[install] - Writing Webdyne config file '/etc/httpd/conf.d/webdyne_conf.pl'.
[install] - Apache uses conf.d directory - not changing httpd.conf file.
[install] - Granting Apache (apache.apache) ownership of cache directory '/var/cache/webdyne'.
[install] - Install completed.

[root@localhost ~]# s<command>ystemctl restart httpd</command></screen></para>

      <para>By default WebDyne will create a cache directory in <filename>/var/cache/webdyne</filename> on Linux systems when a default CPAN install is done (no PREFIX specified). If a PREFIX
      is specified the cache directory will be created as <filename>$PREFIX/cache</filename>. Use the <command>wdapacheinit</command> <option>--cache</option> command-line option to specify an
      alternate location.</para>

      <para>Once <command>wdapacheinit</command> has been run the Apache server should be reloaded or restarted. Use a method appropriate for your Linux distribution.</para>

      <screen>
[root@localhost ~]# <command>systemctl httpd restart</command>
Stopping httpd:                                            [  OK  ]
Starting httpd:                                            [  OK  ]
</screen>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Manual configuration of Apache</title>
        </info>

        <para>If the <command>wdapacheinit</command> command does not work as expected on your system then the Apache config files can be modified manually.</para>

        <para>Include the following section in the Apache httpd.conf file (or create a webdyne.conf file if you distribution supports conf.d style configuration files). These following config
        files are written with Apache 2.4 syntax - adjust path and syntax as required:</para>

        <para><screen>#  Need mod_perl, load up if not already done
#
&lt;IfModule !mod_perl.c&gt;
LoadModule perl_module "/etc/httpd/modules/mod_perl.so"
&lt;/IfModule&gt;

#  Uncomment and update if using a local::lib location for Perl modules
#
#PerlSwitches -I/opt/perl -I/opt/otherperl

#  Preload the WebDyne and WebDyne::Compile module
#
PerlModule    WebDyne WebDyne::Compile

#  Associate psp files with WebDyne
#
AddHandler    modperl    .psp
PerlHandler   WebDyne

#  Set a directory for storage of cache files. Make sure this exists already is writable by the 
#  Apache daemon process.
#
PerlSetVar    WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN    '/opt/webdyne/cache'

#  Allow Apache to access the cache directory if it needs to serve pre-compiled pages from there.
#
&lt;Directory "/opt/webdyne/cache"&gt;
Require all granted
&lt;/Directory&gt;

# Put variables in a separate file - best
#
PerlRequire conf.d/webdyne_constant.pl

#  Or use &lt;Perl&gt; sections - but warning, certbot doesn't like this syntax in http conf files
#
&lt;Perl&gt;

#  Error display/extended display on/off. Set to 1 to enable, 0 to disable
#
$WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SHOW=1;
$WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SHOW_EXTENDED=1;
&lt;/Perl&gt;

</screen></para>

        <important>
          <para>Substitute directory paths in the above example for the relevant/correct/appropriate ones on your system.</para>
        </important>

        <para>Create the cache directory and assign ownership and permission appropriate for your distribution (group name will vary by distribution - locate the correct one for your
        distribution)</para>

        <screen>
[root@localhost ~]# <command>mkdir /opt/webdyne/cache
</command>[root@localhost ~]# <command>chgrp apache /opt/webdyne/cache
</command>[root@localhost ~]# <command>chmod 770 /opt/webdyne/cache
</command></screen>

        <para>Restart Apache and check for any errors.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>PSGI</title>

      <para>Ensure that <productname>Plack</productname> is installed on your system via CPAN:</para>

      <screen># Via CPAN
#
<command>perl -MCPAN -e 'install Plack'</command>
<command>perl -MCPAN -e 'install Plack::Middleware::ForceEnv'</command>

# Modern systems
#
<command>cpan Plack</command>
<command>cpan Plack::Middleware::ForceEnv
</command>
# Or better via CPANM
#
<command>cpanm Plack
cpanm Plack::Middleware::ForceEnv</command></screen>

      <para>You can then start a basic WebDyne server by running the webdyne.psgi command with the --test parameter</para>

      <para><screen><command>webdyne.psgi --test</command></screen></para>

      <para>This will start a PSGI web server on your machine listening to port 5000 (or port 5001 on a Mac). Open a connection to http://127.0.0.1:5000/ or the IP address of your server in
      your web browser to view the test page and validate the WebDyne is working correctly:</para>

      <para><screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/webdyne_psgi1.png" scale="30"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Once verified as working correctly you can serve WebDyne content from a particular directory - or from a single file - using the syntax:</para>

      <screen>#  To serve up all files in a directory:
#
<command>$ webdyne.psgi &lt;directory&gt;</command>

#  E.g serve files in /var/www/html. By default WebDyne will serve app.psp if no filename
#  is specified. If app.psp does not exist a file index will be displayed.
#
<command>$ webdyne.psgi /var/www/html</command>

#  Or just a single app.psp file. Only this file will be served regardless of URL
#
<command>$ webdyne.psgi /var/www/html/time.psp</command></screen>

      <para>The above starts a single-threaded web server using Plack. To start the more performant Starman server (assuming installed):</para>

      <screen>#  Start Starman instance. Substitute port + document root and location of webdyne.psgi
#  as appropriate for your system.
#
$ <command>DOCUMENT_ROOT=/var/www/html starman --port 5001 /usr/local/bin/webdyne.psgi</command></screen>

      <note>
        <para>Plack (via webdyne.psgi) and Starman versions of WebDyne serve basic static files such as css, js, jpg etc. If you want more control over non .psp file you should us best
        practices for service such files via a traditional web server front end. Also note the Starman instance of WebDyne does not support the --test option or indexing - it assumes you are
        running in a production environment and have checked everything with the Plack implementation of webdyne.psgi first.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Numerous options can be set from the command line via environment variables, including Webdyne configuration. See relevant section for all WebDyne configuration options but
      assuming in a local file webdyne.conf.pl:</para>

      <screen>#  Start instance webdyne.psgi using local config file
#
$ <command>WEBDYNE_CONF=./webdyne.conf.pl webdyne.psgi --port=5012 .</command></screen>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Docker</title>

      <para>Docker containers are available from the Github Container Registry. Install the default Docker container (based on Debian) via:</para>

      <screen>#  Default debian version
#
$ <command>docker pull ghcr.io/aspeer/webdyne:latest</command>

#  Or Alpine/Fedora/Perl versions
#
# docker pull ghcr.io/aspeer/webdyne-alpine:latest
# docker pull ghcr.io/aspeer/webdyne-fedora:latest
# docker pull ghcr.io/aspeer/webdyne-perl:latest
</screen>

      <para>Start the docker container with the command:</para>

      <screen>$ docker run -e PORT=5002 -p 5002:5002 --name=webdyne webdyne</screen>

      <para>This will start WebDyne running on port 5002 on the host. Connecting to that location should show the server <emphasis>localtime</emphasis> test page</para>

      <para>To mount a local page and serve it through the docker container use the command:</para>

      <screen>docker run --mount &lt;local_dir&gt;:/app:ro -e PORT=5011 -e DOCUMENT_ROOT=/app -p 5011:5011 --name=webdyne webdyne</screen>

      <para>This will tell docker to mount the local directory into the docker container. If there is a default file named app.psp in the location it will be displayed. If there is a
      <filename>cpanfile</filename> in the mount directory any modules will be installed into the docker container automatically.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Deploying WebDyne apps with Docker</title>

        <para>The WebDyne container can be used as the basis for new docker images containing your application files. Consider the following directory structure (available from Github as <link
        xlink:href="https://github.com/aspeer/psp-WebDyne-Fortune" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">aspeer/psp-WebDyne-Fortune</link>:</para>

        <screen>psp-WebDyne-Fortune/
├── app.pm
├── app.psp
├── cpanfile
├── Dockerfile
└── webdyne.conf.pl

</screen>

        <para>Where:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>app.psp</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The main and default psp file</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>app.pm</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Perl code used in the psp file</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>cpanfile</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A list of Perl modules to be installed in the docker container by cpanm</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Dockerfile</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The docker build file</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>webdyne.conf.pl</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Any variables to be set for the WebDyne environment</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Constitute all the files needed to stand up a WebDyne based application in a Docker container. The contents of the Dockerfile are minimal:</para>

        <screen>FROM webdyne:latest
WORKDIR /app
# Debian packages needed for this app
RUN apt-get update &amp;&amp; apt-get -y install fortunes
COPY app.* .
COPY cpanfile .
COPY webdyne.conf.pl /etc</screen>

        <para>Build the Docker container:</para>

        <screen>docker build  -t webdyne-app-fortune -f ./Dockerfile .</screen>

        <para>And run it:</para>

        <screen>docker run -e PORT=5010 -p 5010:5010 --name=webdyne-app-fortune webdyne-app-fortune</screen>

        <para>Your application should now be available:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/webdyne-app-fortune1.png" scale="30"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="examples">
    <info>
      <title>Basic Usage</title>
    </info>

    <para>Assuming the installation has completed with no errors you are now ready to start creating WebDyne pages and applications.</para>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Integrating Perl into HTML</title>
      </info>

      <para>Some code fragments to give a very high-level overview of how WebDyne can be implemented. First the most basic usage example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Basic Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/hello1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</programlisting><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/hello1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>So far not too exciting - after all we are mixing code and content. Lets try again - the &lt;perl&gt; tag can tag a "handler" attribute which references (calls) a perl subroutine -
      in this case embedded in the .psp file under the __PERL__ token.</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Basic Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/hello2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/hello2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example><note>
          <para>In this case the &lt;perl&gt; tag is implicitly closed (contains no content) as it is assumed all content will be returned by the handler (i.e. the "hello" routine).</para>
        </note></para>

      <para>Better - at least code and content are distinctly separated. Note that whatever the Perl code returns at the end of the routine is what is displayed. Although WebDyne will happily
      display returned strings or scalars, it is more efficient to return a scalar reference, e.g.:</para>

      <para><programlisting language="perl">#  Works
#
sub greeting { print "Hello World" }


#  Is the same as
#
sub greeting { return "Hello World" }
sub greeting { my $var="Hello World"; return $var }


# But best is
#
sub greeting { my $var="Hello World"; return \$var }


# If you don't want to display anything return \undef,
#
sub greeting { return \undef }

</programlisting></para>

      <para>Up until now all the Perl code has been contained within the WebDyne file. The following example shows an instance where the code is contained in a separate Perl module, which
      should be available somewhere in the <filename>@INC</filename> path.</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Basic Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/hello3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/hello3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If not already resident the module (in this case "Digest::MD5") will be loaded by WebDyne, so it must be available somewhere in the <filename>@INC</filename> path. Alternate
      syntaxes are supported - these work in the same way:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Basic Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/hello3a.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/hello3a.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Use of the &lt;perl&gt; tag for in-line code.</title>
        </info>

        <para>The above examples show several variations of the <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tag in use. Perl code that is enclosed by <tag>&lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt;</tag> tags is called
        <emphasis>in-line</emphasis> code:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Basic Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/inline1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/inline1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>This is the most straight-forward use of Perl within a HTML document, but does not really make for easy reading - the Perl code and HTML are intermingled. It may be OK for quick
        scripts etc, but a page will quickly become hard to read if there is a lot of in-line Perl code interspersed between the HTML.</para>

        <para>in-line Perl can be useful if you want a "quick" computation, e.g. insertion of the current year. Note the ability to require external modules via the require attribute, and
        import functions via the import attribute</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Basic Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/inline2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/inline2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>Which can be pretty handy, but looks a bit cumbersome - the tags interfere with the flow of the text, making it harder to read. For this reason in-line perl can also be flagged
        in a WebDyne page using the shortcuts <tag>!{! .. !}</tag>, or by the use of processing instructions (<emphasis role="bold"><tag>&lt;? .. ?&gt;</tag></emphasis>) e.g.:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Basic Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/inline3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/inline3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>The <tag>!{! .. !}</tag> denotation can also be used in tag attributes (processing instructions, and <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tags cannot):</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>In-line code in tag attributes</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/inline4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/inline4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Use of the &lt;perl&gt; tag for non-inline code.</title>
        </info>

        <para>Any code that is not co-mingled with the HTML of a document is <emphasis>non-inline</emphasis> code. It can be segmented from the content HTML using the <token>__PERL__</token>
        delimiter, or by being kept in a completely different package and referenced as an external Perl subroutine call. An example of non-inline code:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/hello2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/hello2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>Note that the <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tag in the above example is explicitly closed and does not contain any content. However non-inline code can enclose HTML or text within the
        tags:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>But this is not very interesting so far - the "Hello World" text is not displayed when the example is run !</para>

        <para>In order for text or HTML within a non-inline perl block to be displayed, it must be "rendered" into the output stream by the WebDyne engine. This is done by calling the
        <methodname>render()</methodname> method. Let's try that again:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>And again, this time showing how to render the text block multiple times. Note that an array reference is returned by the Perl routine - this is fine, and is interpreted as an
        array of HTML text, which is concatenated and send to the browser.</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>Same output using the $self-&gt;print() method:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Perl code example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline3a.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>

        <para>Note that there is a syntactic shortcut available if you have a single handler - just call the subroutine "handler" and it will be invoked by default:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Perl code example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline_handler1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline_handler1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Requiring external modules and importing methods</title>
        </info>

        <para>As noted above inline perl code can import external modules (including any Perl core modules, any module installed via CPAN and/or any module in the normal Perl @INC path or any
        filesystem file). Syntax is as follows:</para>

        <programlisting language="perl">#  Require single module and import single method
#
&lt;perl require="Digest::MD5" import="md5_hex"/&gt;

#  Require single module and import multiple methods
#
&lt;perl require="Digest::MD5" import="md5_hex md5_base64"/&gt;

#  Alternate syntax using array attribute - see later section
#
&lt;perl require="Digest::MD5" import="@{qw(md5_hex md5_base64)}"/&gt;

#  You can also require a file. No import is availanle
#
&lt;perl require="mymodule.pm"&gt;

</programlisting>

        <warning>
          <para>The import functionality is very basic - it only maps to the function in the module, it does not call the actual module import() facility. If the module you are importing does
          something sophisticated in its import() function (such as auto-creating methods) this will not work. Note also nothing is imported by default, even if automatically exported by a
          module.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>So a very basic demo of the above would look as follows:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Perl code example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/require1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/require1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>

        <para>If your module usage and import requirements are more sophisticated they should be put in a __PERL__ section as "normal" code. Anything used or imported will be available to any
        code within the page:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Perl code example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/require2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/require2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>

        <para> </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Alternate output methods from Perl handlers</title>
        </info>

        <para>When calling a perl handler from a .psp file at some stage you will want your code to deliver output to the browser. Various examples have been given throughout this document,
        here is a summary of various output options:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Variations on output options</title>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/output1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/output1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Passing parameters to subroutines</title>
        </info>

        <para>The behaviour of a called <token>__PERL__</token> subroutine can be modified by passing parameters which it can act on:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example with parameters</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline7.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline7.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Parameter inheritance</title>
        </info>

        <para>In-line code can inherit parameters passed from a perl handler/method. In-line code gets two parameters supplied - the first (<varname>$_[0)</varname>) is the self reference
        (e.g. <varname>$self</varname>), the second (<varname>$_[1]</varname>) is any inherited parameters as a hash reference. This can be useful for quick "in-line" formatting, e.g:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code example with parameter inheritance</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/inherit1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/inherit1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Notes about <token>__PERL__</token> sections</title>
        </info>

        <para>Code in <token>__PERL__</token> sections has some particular properties.<token> __PERL__</token> code is only executed once. Subroutines defined in a<token> __PERL__</token>
        section can be called as many times as you want, but the code outside of subroutines is only executed the first time a page is loaded. No matter how many times it is run, in the
        following code <varname>$i</varname> will always be 1:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code variable scope</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>Lexical variables are not accessible outside of the <token>__PERL__</token> section due to the way perl's eval() function works. The following example will fail:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code variable scope</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>Package defined vars declared in a <token>__PERL__</token> section do work, with caveats:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl code variable scope</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/noninline6.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/noninline6.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>See the Variables/Substitution section for clean ways to insert variable contents into the page.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Variables</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne starts to get more useful when variables are used to modify the content of a rendered text block. A simple example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Variable usage</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/var1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/var1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Note the passing of the <parameter>time</parameter> value as a parameter to be substituted when the text is rendered.</para>

      <para>Combine this with multiple call to the <methodname>render()</methodname> routine to display dynamic data:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Variable usage</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/var2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/var2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Variables can also be used to modify tag attributes:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Variable usage</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/var3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/var3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Other variable types are available also, including:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>@{var,var,..}</varname> for arrays, e.g. <varname>@{'foo', 'bar'}</varname></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><varname>%{key=&gt;value, key=&gt;value, ..}</varname> for hashes e.g.<varname> %{ a=&gt;1, b=&gt;2 }</varname></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><varname>+{varname}</varname> for CGI form parameters, e.g. <varname>+{firstname}</varname></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><varname>*{varname} </varname>for environment variables, e.g. <varname>*{HTTP_USER_AGENT}</varname></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><varname>^{requestmethod}</varname> for Apache request (<varname>$r=Apache-&gt;request</varname>) object methods, e.g. <varname>^{protocol}</varname>. Only available for in
          Apache/mod_perl, and only useful for request methods that return a scalar value.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following template uses techniques and tags discussed later, but should provide an example of potential variable usage:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Variable usage</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/var4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/var4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Shortcut Tags</title>
      </info>

      <para>Previous versions of WebDyne used Lincoln Stein's CGI.pm module to render tags, and supported CGI.pm shortcut tags such as &lt;start_html&gt;, &lt;popup_menu&gt; etc. Modern
      versions of WebDyne do not use CGI.pm in any modules, having ported tag generation to HTML::Tiny. Support for shortcut tags is preserved though - they provide a quick and easy way to
      generate simple web pages.</para>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Quick pages using shortcut <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag>, <tag>&lt;end_html&gt;</tag> tags</title>
        </info>

        <para>For rapid development you can take advantage of the <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> and <tag>&lt;end_html&gt;</tag> tags. The following page generates compliant HTML (view the page
        source after loading it to see for yourself):</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Shortcut tags</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi6.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi6.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>The <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> tag generates all the <tag>&lt;html&gt;</tag>, <tag>&lt;head&gt;</tag>, <tag>&lt;title&gt;</tag> tags etc needed for a valid HTML page plus an
        opening body tag. Just enter the body content, then optionally finish with <tag>&lt;end_html&gt;</tag> to generate the closing <tag>&lt;body&gt;</tag> and <tag>&lt;html&gt;</tag> tags
        (optional because the page is automatically closed if these are omitted). See the tag reference section but here is an example using several of the properties available in the
        <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> tag including loading multiple scripts and stylesheets:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>Shortcut tags</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/start_html1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/start_html1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>

        <caution>
          <para>If make sure any attributes using the <parameter>@{..}</parameter> or <parameter>%{..}</parameter> convention are on one line - the parser will not interpret them correctly if
          spanning multiple lines.</para>
        </caution>

        <para>If using the <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> shortcut tag you can optionally insert default stylesheets and/or <tag>&lt;head&gt;</tag> sections from the Webdyne configuration file.
        E.g if in your <filename>webdyne.conf.pl</filename> file you have the following:</para>

        <screen>$_={
    'WebDyne::Constant' =&gt; {

        #  Inserted as &lt;meta&gt; into &lt;head&gt; section
        #
        WEBDYNE_META =&gt; {
            #  These all rendered as &lt;meta name="$key" content="$value"&gt;
            viewport =&gt; 'width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0',
            author =&gt; 'Bob Foobar',
            #  This one rendered as &lt;meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="IE=edge"&gt;
            'http-equiv=X-UA-Compatible' =&gt; 'IE=edge',
            'http-equiv=refresh' =&gt; '5; url=https://www.example.com'
        }

        #  This is inserted inside the &lt;html&gt; starting tag, works for &lt;start_html&gt; or straight &lt;html&gt;
        #
        WEBDYNE_HTML_PARAM =&gt; {
            lang =&gt; 'de'
        }

        #  This is inserted before the &lt;/head&gt; closing tag, works for &lt;start_html&gt; or straight &lt;html&gt;
        #
        WEBDYNE_HEAD_INSERT =&gt; &lt;&lt; 'END'
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/@picocss/pico@2/css/pico.classless.min.css"&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
:root { --pico-font-size: 85% } 
body { padding-top: 10px; padding-left: 10px;
&lt;/style&gt;
END
    
    }
}</screen>

        <para>Then any <filename>.psp</filename> file with a <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> tag will have the following content:</para>

        <screen>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;&lt;html lang="de"&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Untitled Document&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"&gt;
&lt;meta name="author" content="Bob Foobar"&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="refresh" content="5; url=https://www.example.com"&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="IE=edge"&gt;
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/@picocss/pico@2/css/pico.classless.min.css"&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    :root { --pico-font-size: 85% } 
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
</screen>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>HTML Forms using &lt;popup_menu&gt;,&lt;checkbox_group&gt; and other tags</title>

        <para>The CGI.pm module presented several shortcut tags for generating HTML forms. These tags have been recreated in WebDyne and act in a similar way.</para>

        <para>The manual page for CGI.pm contains the following synopsis example:</para>

        <example>
          <info>
            <title>CGI.pm Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting>use CGI qw/:standard/;
   print header,
         start_html('A Simple Example'),
         h1('A Simple Example'),
         start_form,
         "What's your name? ",textfield('name'),p,
         "What's the combination?", p,
         checkbox_group(-name=&gt;'words',
                        -values=&gt;['eenie','meenie','minie','moe'],
                        -defaults=&gt;['eenie','minie']), p,
         "What's your favorite color? ",
         popup_menu(-name=&gt;'color',
                    -values=&gt;['red','green','blue','chartreuse']),p,
         submit,
         end_form,
         hr;

    if (param()) {
        print "Your name is",em(param('name')),p,
              "The keywords are: ",em(join(", ",param('words'))),p,</programlisting></para>
        </example>

        <para>If the example was ported to a WebDyne compatible page it might look something like this:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>CGI Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <note>
          <para>When using the WebDyne form tags, state (previous form values) are preserved after the Submit button is presented. This makes building single page application simple as there
          is no need to implement logic to adjust options in a traditional HTML form to reflect the user's choice.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>More on HTML shortcut tags in forms</title>
        </info>

        <para>Tags such as <tag>&lt;popup_menu&gt;</tag> output traditional HTML form tags such as <tag>&lt;select&gt;&lt;option&gt;...&lt;/select&gt;</tag>, but they have the advantage of
        allowing Perl data types as attributes. Take the following example:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;popup_menu value="%{red=&gt;Red, green=&gt;Green, blue=&gt;Blue}"/&gt;

</screen>

        <para>it is arguably easier to read than:</para>

        <screen>
&lt;select name="values" tabindex="1"&gt;
&lt;option value="green"&gt;Green&lt;/option&gt;
&lt;option value="blue"&gt;Blue&lt;/option&gt;
&lt;option value="red"&gt;Red&lt;/option&gt;
&lt;/select&gt;

</screen>

        <para>So there is some readability benefit, however the real advantage shows when we consider the next example:<example>
            <info>
              <title>Dynamic tag attributes</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>All values for the menu item were pre-populated from one WebDyne variable - which saves a significant amount of time populating a "countries" style drop-down box.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Access to HTML form responses and query strings</title>
        </info>

        <para>Once a form is submitted you will want to act on responses. There are several ways to do this - you can access a CGI::Simple object instance in any WebDyne template by calling
        the CGI() method to obtain form responses:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Access to CGI object</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>

        <para>From there you can all any method supported by the CGI::Simple module - see the CGI::Simple manual page (<command>man CGI::Simple</command>) or review on CPAN: <link
        xlink:href="https://metacpan.org/pod/CGI::Simple" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CGI::Simple</link></para>

        <para>Since one of the most common code tasks is to access query parameters, WebDyne stores them in the special <varname>%_</varname> global variable before any user defined Perl
        methods are called. For example:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>Perl CGI access</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Advanced Usage</title>
    </info>

    <para>A lot of tasks can be achieved just using the basic features detailed above. However there are more advanced features that can make life even easier</para>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Blocks</title>
      </info>

      <para>Blocks are a powerful dynamic content generation tool. WebDyne can render arbitrary blocks of text or HTML within a page, which makes generation of dynamic content generally more
      readable than similar output generated within Perl code. An example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Blocks</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>There can be more than one block with the same name - any block with the target name will be rendered:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Blocks</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Like any other text or HTML between <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tags, blocks can take parameters to substitute into the text:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Blocks</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Blocks have a non-intuitive feature - they still display even if they are outside of the <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tags that made the call to render them. e.g. the following is
      OK:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Blocks</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>You can mix the two styles:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Blocks</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>You can use the &lt;block&gt; tag display attribute to hide or show a block, or use a CGI parameter to determine visibility (e.g for a status update or warning):</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Blocks</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/block_toggle1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/block_toggle1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>File inclusion</title>
      </info>

      <para>You can include other file fragments at compile time using the include tag:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Include</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/include1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/include1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If the file name is not an absolute path name is will be loaded relative to the directory of the parent file. For example if file "bar.psp" incorporates the tag <tag>&lt;include
      file="foo.psp"&gt;</tag> it will be expected that "<filename>foo.psp</filename>" is in the same directory as "<filename>bar.psp</filename>".</para>

      <para><important>
          <para>The include tag pulls in the target file at compile time. Changes to the included file after the WebDyne page is run the first time (resulting in compilation) are not reflected
          in subsequent output unless the <parameter>nocache</parameter> attribute is set. Thus the include tag should not be seen as a shortcut to a pseudo Content Management System. For
          example <tag>&lt;include file="latest_news.txt"&gt;</tag> will probably not behave in the way you expect. The first time you run it the latest news is displayed. However updating the
          "latest_news.txt" file will not result in changes to the output (it will be stale).</para>

          <para>If you do use the <parameter>nocache</parameter> attribute the included page will be loaded and parsed every time, significantly slowing down page display. There are betters
          ways to build a CMS with WebDyne - use the include tag sparingly !</para>
        </important></para>

      <para>You can include just the head or body section of a HTML or PSP file by using the head or body attributes. Here is the reference file (file to be included). It does not have to be a
      .psp file - a standard HTML file can be supplied :</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Include</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/include2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/include2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>And here is the generating file (the file that includes sections from the reference file).</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Include</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/include3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/include3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>You can also include block sections from <filename>.psp</filename> files. If this is the reference file (the file to be included) containing two blocks. This is a renderable
      <filename>.psp</filename> file in it's own right. The blocks use the <parameter>display</parameter> attribute to demonstrate that they will produce output, but it's not required:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Include</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/include4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/include4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>And here is the file that brings in the blocks from the reference file and incorporates them into the output:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Include</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/include5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/include5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title xml:id="static_sections">Static Sections</title>
      </info>

      <para>Sometimes you want to generate dynamic output in a page once only (e.g. a last modified date, a sidebar menu etc.) Using WebDyne this can be done with Perl or CGI code flagged with
      the "static" attribute. Any dynamic tag so flagged will be rendered at compile time, and the resulting output will become part of the compiled page - it will not change on subsequent
      page views, or have to be re-run each time the page is loaded. An example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/static1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/static1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>In fact the above page will render very quickly because it has no dynamic content at all once the &lt;perl&gt; content is flagged as static. The WebDyne engine will recognise this
      and store the page as a static HTML file in its cache. Whenever it is called WebDyne will use the Apache lookup_file() function to return the page as if it was just serving up static
      content.</para>

      <para>You can check this by looking at the content of the WebDyne cache directory (usually /var/webdyne/cache). Any file with a ".html" extension represents the static version of a
      page.</para>

      <para>Of course you can still mix static and dynamic Perl sections:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/static2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/static2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If you want the whole pages to be static, then flagging everything with the "static" attribute can be cumbersome. There is a special meta tag which flags the entire page as
      static:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/static3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/static3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If you don't like the idea of setting the static flag in meta data, then "using" the special package "WebDyne::Static" will have exactly the same effect:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/static3a.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/static3a.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If the static tag seems trivial consider the example that displayed country codes:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cgi5.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cgi5.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>Every time the above example is viewed the Country Name list is generated dynamically via the Locale::Country module. This is a waste of resources because the list changes very
      infrequently. We can keep the code neat but gain a lot of speed by adding the <option>static</option> tag attribute:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Static</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/static4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/static4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>By simply adding the "static" attribute output on a sample machine resulted in a 4x speedup in page loads. Judicious use of the static tag in places with slow changing data can
      markedly increase efficiency of the WebDyne engine.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title xml:id="caching_section">Caching</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne has the ability to cache the compiled version of a dynamic page according to specs you set via the API. When coupled with pages/blocks that are flagged as static this
      presents some powerful possibilities.<important>
          <para>Caching will only work if <varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN</varname> is defined and set to a directory that the web server has write access to. If caching does not work check that
          $<varname>WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN</varname> is defined and permissions set correctly for your web server.</para>
        </important></para>

      <para>There are many potential examples, but consider this one: you have a page that generates output by making a complex query to a database, which takes a lot of CPU and disk IO
      resources to generate. You need to update the page reasonably frequently (e.g. a weather forecast, near real time sales stats), but can't afford to have the query run every time someone
      view the page.</para>

      <para>WebDyne allows you to configure the page to cache the output for a period of time (say 5 minutes) before re-running the query. In this way users sees near real-time data without
      imposing a high load on the database/Web server.</para>

      <para>WebDyne knows to enable the caching code by looking for a meta tag, or by loading the <classname>WebDyne::Cache</classname> module in a <token>__PERL__</token> block.</para>

      <para>The cache code can command WebDyne to recompile a page based on any arbitrary criteria it desires. As an example the following code will recompile the page every 10 seconds. If
      viewed in between refresh intervals WebDyne will serve up the cached HTML result using Apache r$-&gt;lookup_file() or the FCGI equivalent, which is very fast.</para>

      <para>Try it by running the following example and clicking refresh a few times over a 20 second interval</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Caching</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cache1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cache1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>WebDyne uses the return value of the nominated cache routine to determine what UID (unique ID) to assign to the page. In the above example we returned \undef, which signifies that
      the UID will remain unchanged.</para>

      <para>You can start to get more advanced in your handling of cached pages by returning a different UID based on some arbitrary criteria. To extend our example above: say we have a page
      that generated sales figures for a given month. The SQL code to do this takes a long time, and we do not want to hit the database every time someone loads up the page. However we cannot
      just cache the output, as it will vary depending on the month the user chooses. We can tell the cache code to generate a different UID based on the month selected, then cache the
      resulting output.</para>

      <para>The following example simulates such a scenario:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Caching</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/cache2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/cache2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para><important>
          <para>Take care when using user-supplied input to generate the page UID. There is no inbuilt code in WebDyne to limit the number of UID's associated with a page. Unless we check it,
          a malicious user could potentially DOS the server by supplying endless random "months" to the above page with a script, causing WebDyne to create a new file for each UID - perhaps
          eventually filling the disk partition that holds the cache directory. That is why we check the month is valid in the code above.</para>
        </important></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JSON</title>

      <para>WebDyne has a &lt;json&gt; tag that can be used to present JSON data objects to Javascript libraries in an output page. Here is a very simple example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>JSON Chart</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/chart1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/chart1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>If you run it and review the source HTML you will see the JSON data rendered into the page as <tag>&lt;script&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</tag> block of type application/json with an
      id of "chartData". Any data returned by the perl routine nominated by the json tag is presented as JSON within that tag block, and available to Javascript libraries within the page. JSON
      data is kept in canononical order by default, which can be adjusted with the WEBDYNE_JSON_CANONICAL variable if not desired/needed for a very small speed-up.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>API Tags</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne has the ability to make available a basic REST API facility using the <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tag in conjunction with the Router::Simple CPAN module. Documents that utilise
      the <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tag are somewhat unique in that:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>There is no need for any other tags in the document besides the <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tag. All other tags are ignored - in fact they are discarded.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any .psp file file an <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tag will only emit JSON data with a content type of "<type>application/json</type>"</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The REST api path must correspond .psp file at some path level, e.g. if your path is <filename>/api/user/42</filename> you must have a file called either
          "<filename>api.psp</filename>" or "<filename>api/user.psp</filename>" in your path.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A .psp file can contain multiple <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tags corresponding to different <classname>Router::Simple</classname> routes</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Here is a very simple example. Note the format of the URL in the Run hyperlink:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>API Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/api.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/api/uppercase/bob/42" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run uppercase API example</link></para>

        <para><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/api/doublecase/bob/42" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run doublecase API example</link></para>
      </example>

      <caution>
        <para>The <tag>&lt;api&gt;</tag> tag is still somewhat experimental. Use with caution</para>
      </caution>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>HTMX</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne has support for <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> tags to supply fragmented HTML to pages using the <link xlink:href="https://htmx.org"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">HTMX Javascript Library</link>. WebDyne can support just supplying HTML snippet to pages in response to htmx calls. HTMX and WebDyne are
      complementary libraries which can be combined together to support dynamic pages with in-place updates from WebDybe Perl backends. Here is a simple HTML file
      (<filename>htmx_demo1.psp</filename>) incorporating HTMX calls to a backend file called <filename>htmx_time1.psp</filename>. Here is the display file,
      <filename>htmx_demo1.psp</filename></para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>HTMX Example</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_demo1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_demo1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example>And the backend file which generates the HTMX data for the above page (<filename>htmx_time1.psp</filename>):</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>HTMX Example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_time1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_time1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>Note the <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> tags. You can run the above htmx resource file and it will render correctly as a full HTML page - however if WebDyne detects a 'hx-request' HTTP
      header it will only send the fragment back.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Only one <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> section from a file will ever be rendered. You can have multiple <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> sections in a .psp file however only one can be rendered
        at any time. You can use the display attribute with dynamic matching (see later) do render different <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> sections in a .psp file, or you can keep them all in
        different files (e.g. one <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> section per .psp file</para>
      </important>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Using Perl within &lt;htmx&gt; tags</title>
        </info>

        <para><tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> tags can be called with the same attributes as <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tags, including nominating a handler to generate data. See the following
        example:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>HTMX Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_demo2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_demo2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example>And the backend file which generates the HTMX data for the above page - now with the HTML fragment generated by Perl:<example>
            <info>
              <title>HTMX Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_time2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_time2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using multiple <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> tags in one .psp file</title>

        <para>As is mentioned above only one <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> fragment can be returned by a .psp page at a time - but you can use techniques to select which tag should be rendered. The
        <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> tag supports the display attribute. If this attribute exists and is a "true" value then the <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> fragment will be returned. At first this
        doesn't seem very useful - but when combined with dynamic evaluation via either page query parameters or <code>!{! .. !}</code> evaluation it becomes more compelling. Take the
        following two button example:</para>

        <para><example>
            <info>
              <title>HTMX Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_demo3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_demo3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example><example>
            <info>
              <title>HTMX Example</title>
            </info>

            <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/htmx_time3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
            xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/htmx_time3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
          </example>Normally you would expect to have the hx-get attribute for each button go to a different .psp page. But in this instance they refer to the same page. So how do we
        discriminate ? The key is in the supply of the hx-vals attribute, which allows us to send query strings to the htmx resource page. We can then use them to select which &lt;htmx&gt;
        block is returned.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Note the use of <code>js:{ &lt;json&gt; }</code> notation in the <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag> <parameter>hx-vals</parameter> attribute. It allows for easier supply of JSON data
          without needed to manipulate/escape double-quotes in raw JSON data. You'll also note there is no <tag>&lt;start_html&gt;</tag> tag. It's not necessary for <tag>&lt;htmx&gt;</tag>
          pages.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Dump</title>
      </info>

      <para>The <tag>&lt;dump&gt;</tag> tag is a informational element which can be included in a page for diagnostic or debugging purposes. It will show various variable and state values for
      the page. By default if a <tag>&lt;dump&gt;</tag> flag is embedded in a page diagnostic information is not shown unless the <parameter>force</parameter> attribute is specified or the
      <constant>$WEBDYNE_DUMP_FLAG</constant> is set, the latter allowing the <tag>&lt;dump&gt;</tag> tag to be embedded into all pages on a site but not activated unless debugging
      enabled.</para>

      <para>Various diagnostic elements can be displayed - see the &lt;dump&gt; tag section for information on what they are. In this example all components are enabled and display is
      forced:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Dump example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/dump1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/dump1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>Dump display/hide can be controlled by form parameters or run URI query strings. In the example below ticking the checkbox or simply appending "?dump_enable=1" to the URL will
      display the dump information:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Dump example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/dump2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/dump2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Error Handling</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Error Messages</title>
      </info>

      <para>Sooner or later something is going to go wrong in your code. If this happens WebDyne will generate an error showing what the error was and attempting to give information on where
      it came from: Take the following example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Error handling</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/err1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/err1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>If you run the above example an error message will be displayed</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/err1.png" scale="50"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>In this example the backtrace is within in-line code, so all references in the backtrace are to internal WebDyne modules. The code fragment will show the line with the
      error.</para>

      <para>If we have a look at another example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <info>
            <title>Intentional die()</title>
          </info>

          <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/err2.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting><link
          xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/err2.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
        </example></para>

      <para>And the corresponding screen shot:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/err2.png" scale="50"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>We can see that the error occurred in the "hello" subroutine (invoked at line 2 of the page) within the perl block on line 9. The 32 digit hexadecimal number is the page unique ID
      - it is different for each page. WebDyne runs the code for each page in a package name space that includes the page's UID - in this way pages with identical subroutine names (e.g. two
      pages with a "hello" subroutine) can be accommodated with no collision.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Exceptions</title>
      </info>

      <para>Errors (exceptions) can be generated within a WebDyne page in two ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>By calling die() as shown in example above.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>By returning an error message via the err() method, exported by default.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Examples</para>

      <para><programlisting>__PERL__


#  Good
#
sub hello {

    return err('no foobar') if !$foobar;

}

# Also OK
#
sub hello {

    return die('no foobar') if !$foobar;

}</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Error Checking</title>
      </info>

      <para>So far all the code examples have just assumed that any call to a WebDyne API method has been successful - no error checking is done. WebDyne always returns "undef" if an API
      method call fails - which should be checked for after every call in a best practice scenario.</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Error checking</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/err3.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting> <link
        xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/err3.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>You can use the err() function to check for errors in WebDyne Perl code associated with a page, e.g.:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Error throw</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/err4.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting></para>

        <para><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/err4.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>Note that the backtrace in this example shows clearly where the error was triggered from.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>WebDyne API</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne tags</title>
      </info>

      <para>Reference of WebDyne tags and supported attributes</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;perl&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run Perl code either in-line (between the &lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt;) tags, or non-inline via the method attribute</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>method|handler=method</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Call an external Perl subroutine in from a module, or a subroutine in a __PERL__ block at the of the .psp file. If the handler is specified a module call (e.g.
                  Digest::MD5::md5_hex()) then a require call will be load the module (Digest::MD5 in this example.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>package|require=[Module::Name] | [Path/Filename.pm]</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Load a Perl module or file needed to support a method call. E.g. &lt;perl require=Digest::MD5/&gt; to load the Digest::MD5 module. Anything with a [./\] character is
                  treated as file patch to a Perl file (e.g. "/home/user/module.pm"), otherwise it is treated as module name ("Digest::MD5")</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>import=[function], &lt;function&gt;, &lt;function&gt; ..</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Import a single or multiple functions into the file namespace. Use "import=name" for a single function, or pass an array ref (import="@{name1, name2}" for multiple
                  functions. E.g. &lt;perl require="Digest::SHA" import="@{qw(sha1 sha1_hex)}"/&gt;. Functions are then available anywhere in the file namespace.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>param=scalar|array|hash</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Parameters to be supplied to perl routine. Supply array and hash using "@{1,2}" and "%{a=&gt;1, b=&gt;2}" conventions respectively, e.g. &lt;perl method="sum2num"
                  param="@{2,2}"/&gt;</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>static=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>This Perl code to be run once only and the output cached for all subsequent requests.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>file=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Force package|require attribute to be treated as a file, even if it appears to "look like" a module name to the loader. Rarely needed, use case would be a Perl module
                  in the current directory without an extension.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>hidden=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The output from the Perl module will be hidden.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;json&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run Perl code similar to &lt;perl&gt; tag but expect code to return a HASH or ARRAY ref and encode into JSON, outputting in a &lt;script&gt; tag with type="application/json".
            When supplied with an id attribute this data can be used by any Javascript function in the page. All attributes are the same as the &lt;perl&gt; tag with the following extra
            attribute</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>id=[name]</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>ID this &lt;script&gt; tag will be given, e.g. &lt;script id="mydata" type="application/json"&gt;[{"foo":1}]&lt;/script&gt;</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;block&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Block of HTML code to be optionally rendered if desired by call to <methodname>render_block</methodname> Webdyne method:</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>name=identifier</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>Mandatory.</emphasis> The name for this block of HTML. Referenced when rendering a particular block in perl code, e.g. return
                  $self-&gt;render_block("foo");</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>display=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Force display of this block even if not invoked by render_block WebDyne method. Useful for prototyping.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>static=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>This block rendered once only and the output cached for all subsequent requests</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;include&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Include HTML or text from an external file. This includes pulling in the &lt;head&gt; or &lt;body&gt; section from another HTML or .psp file. If pulled in from a .psp file it
            will compiled and interpreted in the context of the current page.</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>file=filename</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>Mandatory</emphasis>. Name of file we want to include. Can be relative to current directory or absolute path.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>head=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>File is an HTML or <filename>.psp</filename> file and we want to include just the <tag>&lt;head&gt;</tag> section</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>body=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>File is an HTML or <filename>.psp</filename> file and we want to include just the <tag>&lt;body&gt;</tag> section.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>block=blockname</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>File is a <filename>.psp</filename> file and we want to include a <tag>&lt;block&gt;</tag> section from that file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>nocache</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Don't cache the results of the include, bring them in off disk each time. Will incur performance penalty</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;api&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Respond to a JSON request made from a client.</para>

            <para><variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>pattern=string</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Mandatory</emphasis>. Name of <classname>Route::Simple</classname> pattern we want to serve, e.g. /api/{user}/:id</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>destination | dest | data=hash ref</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Hash we want to supply to perl routine if match made. See <classname>Route::Simple</classname></para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term>option=hash ref</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Match options, GET, PUT etc. <classname>Route::Simple</classname></para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;htmx&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Serve HTML snippets. Takes exactly the same parameters as the <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> tag with one addition</para>

            <para><variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>display=boolean</term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. If evaluates to true then this &lt;htmx&gt; snippet fires. Only tag can respond per page. Use this attribute in conjunction with
                    dynamic evaluation (e.g. display="!{! $_{name} eq 'Bob' !}")</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>&lt;dump&gt;</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Display CGI parameters in dump format via CGI::Simple-&gt;Dump call. Useful for debugging. Only rendered if <varname>$WEBDYNE_DUMP_FLAG</varname> global set to 1 in WebDyne
            constants of the display|force attribute specified (see below). Useful while troubleshooting or debugging pages.</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>display|force=1</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis>Optional.</emphasis> Force display even if <varname>$WEBDYNE_DUMP_FLAG</varname> global not set</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>all</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Display all diagnostic blocks</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>cgi</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Display CGI parameters and query strings</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>env</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Display environment variables</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>constant</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Display Webdyne constants</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>version</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Display version strings</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne methods</title>
      </info>

      <para>When running Perl code within a WebDyne page the very first parameter passed to any routine (in-line or in a __PERL__ block) is an instance of the WebDyne page object (referred to
      as <varname>$self</varname> in most of the examples). All methods return <returnvalue>undef</returnvalue> on failure, and raise an error using the <function>err()</function> function.
      The following methods are available to any instance of the WebDyne object:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>CGI()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns an instance of the CGI::Simple object for the current request.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>r(), request()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns an instance of the Apache request object, or a mock object with similar functionality when running under PSGI or FCGI</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>html_tiny()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns an instance of the HTML::Tiny object, can be used for creating programmatic HTML output</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>include()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns HTML derived from a file, using the same parameters as the <tag>&lt;include&gt;</tag> tag</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>render( <replaceable>key=&gt;value, key=&gt;value</replaceable>, .. )</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Called to render the text or HTML between <tag>&lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt;</tag> tags. Optional key and value pairs will be substituted into the output as per the variable
            section. Returns a scalar ref of the resulting HTML.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>render_block( blockname, <replaceable>key=&gt;value, key=&gt;value, ..</replaceable>).</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Called to render a block of text or HTML between &lt;block&gt;..&lt;/block&gt; tags. Optional key and value pairs will be substituted into the output as per the variable
            section. Returns scalar ref of resulting HTML if called with from &lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt; section containing the block to be rendered, or true (\undef) if the block is not
            within the &lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt; section (e.g. further into the document, see the block section for an example).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>render_reset()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Erase anything previously set to render - it will not be sent to the browser.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>redirect( uri=&gt;uri | file=&gt;filename | html=&gt;\html_text | json=&gt;\json_text | text=&gt;\plain_text)</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Will redirect to URI or file nominated, or display only nominated text. Any rendering done to prior to this method is abandoned. If supplying HTML text to be rendered supply
            as a SCALAR reference.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>inode( <replaceable>seed</replaceable> )</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns the page unique ID (UID). Called inode for legacy reasons, as that is what the UID used to be based on. If a seed value is supplied a new UID will be generated based
            on an MD5 of the seed. Seed only needs to be supplied if using advanced cache handlers.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>cache_mtime( <replaceable>uid</replaceable> )</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns the mtime (modification time) of the cache file associated with the optionally supplied UID. If no UID supplied the current one will be used. Can be used to make
            cache compile decisions by WebDyne::Cache code (e.g if page &gt; x minutes old, recompile).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>source_mtime()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Returns the mtime (modification time) of the source .psp file currently being rendered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>cache_compile()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Force recompilation of cache file. Can be used in cache code to force recompilation of a page, even if it is flagged static. Returns current value if no parameters supplied,
            or sets if parameter supplied.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>filename()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Return the full filename (including path) of the file being rendered. Will only return the core (main) filename - any included files, templates etc. are not reported.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>cwd()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Return the current working directory WebDyne is operating in.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>no_cache()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Send headers indicating that the page is not be cached by the browser or intermediate proxies. By default WebDyne pages automatically set the no-cache headers, although this
            behaviour can be modified by clearing the <varname>$WEBDYNE_NO_CACHE</varname> variable and using this function</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>meta()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Return a hash ref containing the meta data for this page. Alterations to meta data are persistent for this process, and carry across Apache requests (although not across
            different Apache processes)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>print(), printf(), say()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Render the output of the <methodname>print()</methodname>, <methodname>printf()</methodname> or <methodname>say()</methodname> routines into the current HTML stream. The
            <methodname>print()</methodname> and <methodname>printf()</methodname> methods emulate their Perl functions in not appending a new line into the output, where as
            <methodname>say()</methodname> does.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>render_time()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Return the elapsed time since the WebDyne hander started rendering this page. Obviously only meaningful if called at the end of a page, just before final output to
            browser.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="webdyne_constants">
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne Constants</title>
      </info>

      <para>Constants defined in the WebDyne::Constant package control various aspects of how WebDyne behaves. Constants can be modified globally by altering a global configuration file
      (<filename>/etc/webdyne.conf.pl</filename> under Linux distros), setting environment variable or by altering configuration parameters within the Apache web server config.</para>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Global constants file</title>
        </info>

        <para>WebDyne will look for a system constants file under <filename>/etc/webdyne.conf.pl</filename> and set package variables according to values found in that file. The file is in
        Perl Data::Dumper format, and takes the format:</para>

        <programlisting># sample /etc/webdyne.conf.pl file
#
$VAR1={
        WebDyne::Constant =&gt; {

                WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN       =&gt; '/data1/webdyne/cache',
                WEBDYNE_STORE_COMMENTS =&gt; 1,
                #  ... more variables for WebDyne package

       },

       WebDyne::Session::Constant =&gt; {

                WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME =&gt; 'session_cookie',
                #  ... more variables for WebDyne::Session package

       },

};</programlisting>

        <para>The file is not present by default and should be created if you wish to change any of the WebDyne constants from their default values.</para>

        <important>
          <para>Always check the syntax of the <filename>/etc/webdyne.conf.pl</filename> file after editing by running <command>perl -c -w /etc/webdyne.conf.pl</command> to check that the file
          is readable by Perl. Files with syntax errors will fail silently and the variables will revert to module defaults.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Setting WebDyne constants in Apache</title>
        </info>

        <para>WebDyne constants can be set in an Apache httpd.conf file using the PerlSetVar directive:</para>

        <para><programlisting>
PerlHandler     WebDyne
PerlSetVar      WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN                '/data1/webdyne/cache'
PerlSetVar      WEBDYNE_STORE_COMMENTS          1

#  From WebDyne::Session package
#
PerlSetVar      WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME  'session_cookie'

</programlisting></para>

        <para><important>
            <para>WebDyne constants cannot be set on a per-location or per-directory basis - they are read from the top level of the config file and set globally.</para>

            <para>Some 1.x versions of mod_perl do not read PerlSetVar variables correctly. If you encounter this problem use a <tag>&lt;Perl&gt;..&lt;/Perl&gt;</tag> section in the
            <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file, e.g.:</para>

            <programlisting># Mod_perl 1.x

PerlHandler     WebDyne
&lt;Perl&gt;
$WebDyne::Constant::WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN='/data1/webdyne/cache';
$WebDyne::Constant::WEBDYNE_STORE_COMMENTS=1;
$WebDyne::Session::Constant::WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME='session_cookie';
&lt;/Perl&gt;

</programlisting>
          </important></para>

        <para>Where you need to set variables without simple string content you can use a <tag>&lt;Perl&gt;..&lt;/Perl&gt;</tag> section in the <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file,
        e.g.:</para>

        <programlisting># Setting more complex variables

PerlHandler     WebDyne
&lt;Perl&gt;
$WebDyne::Constant::WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN='/data1/webdyne/cache';
$WebDyne::Constant::WEBDYNE_STORE_COMMENTS=1;
$WebDyne::Session::Constant::WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME='session_cookie';
&lt;/Perl&gt;

</programlisting>

        <warning>
          <para>The letsencrypt <command>certbot</command> utility will error out when trying to update any Apache config file with <code>&lt;Perl&gt;</code> sections. To avoid this you put
          the variables in a separate file and include them, e.g. in the <filename>apache.conf</filename> file:</para>

          <para><programlisting># Some config setting defaults. See documentation for full range. 
# Commented out # options represent defaults 
#
PerlRequire conf.d/webdyne_constant.pl</programlisting></para>

          <para>And then in the webdyne_constant.pl file:</para>

          <para><programlisting>use WebDyne;
use WebDyne::Constant;

#  Error display/extended display on/off. More granular options below. 
#  Set to 1 to enable, 0 to disable
#
$WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SHOW=1;
$WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SHOW_EXTENDED=1;

#  Extended error control.
#
#  $WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_SHOW=1;
#  $WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_LINES_PRE=4;
#  $WebDyne::WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_LINES_POST=4;
</programlisting></para>
        </warning>
      </section>

      <section>
        <info>
          <title>Constants Reference</title>
        </info>

        <para>The following constants can be altered to change the behaviour of the WebDyne package. All these constants reside in the <classname>WebDyne::Constant</classname> package
        namespace.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_DN</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The name of the directory that will hold partially compiled WebDyne cache files. Must exist and be writable by the Apache process</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_STARTUP_CACHE_FLUSH</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove all existing disk cache files at Apache startup. 1=yes (default), 0=no. By default all disk cache files are removed at startup, and thus pages must be recompiled
              again the first time they are viewed. If you set this to 0 (no) then disk cache files will be saved between startups and pages will not need to be re-compiled if Apache is
              restarted.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_CHECK_FREQ</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Check the memory cache after this many request (per-process counter). default=256. After this many requests a housekeeping function will check compiled pages that are
              stored in memory and remove old ones according to the criteria below.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_HIGH_WATER</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove compiled from pages from memory when we have more than this many. default=64</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_LOW_WATER</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>After reaching HIGH_WATER delete until we get down to this amount. default=32</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CACHE_CLEAN_METHOD</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Clean algorithm. default=1, means least used cleaned first, 0 means oldest last view cleaned first</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_EVAL_SAFE</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>default=0 (no), If set to 1 means eval in a Safe.pm container. Evaluating code in a Safe container is experimental and not supported or recommended for general WebDyne
              use.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_EVAL_SAFE_OPCODE_AR</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The opcode set to use in Safe.pm evals (see the Safe man page). Defaults to "[':default']". Use [&amp;Opcode::full_opset()] for the full opset. CAUTION Use of WebDyne with
              Safe.pm not comprehensively tested and considered experimental.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_EVAL_USE_STRICT</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The string to use before each eval. Defaults to "use strict qw(vars);". Set to undef if you do not want strict.pm. In Safe mode this becomes a flag only - set undef for "no
              strict", and non-undef for "use strict" equivalence in a Safe mode (checked under Perl 5.8.6 only, results in earlier versions of Perl may vary).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_STRICT_VARS</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Check if a var is declared in a render block (e.g $ {foo}) but not supplied as a render parameter. If so will throw an error. Set to 0 to ignore. default=1</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_DUMP_FLAG</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If 1, any instance of the special &lt;dump&gt; tag will print out results from CGI-&gt;dump(). Use when debugging forms. default=0</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_DTD</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The DTD to place at the top of a rendered page. Defaults to: &lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_HTML_PARAM</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>attributes for the &lt;html&gt; tag, default is { lang =&gt;'en' }</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_HEAD_INSERT</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Any HTML you want inserted before the closing <tag>&lt;/head&gt;</tag> tag, e.g. stylesheet or script includes to be added to every <filename>.psp</filename> page. Must be
              valid HTML &lt;head&gt; directives, not interpreted or compiled by WebDyne, incorporated as-is</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_COMPILE_IGNORE_WHITESPACE</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Ignore source file whitespace as per HTML::TreeBuilder ignore_ignorable_whitespace function. Defaults to 1</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_COMPILE_NO_SPACE_COMPACTING</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Do not compact source file whitespace as per HTML::TreeBuilder no_space_compacting function. Defaults to 0</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_STORE_COMMENTS</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>By default comments are not rendered. Set to 1 to store and display comments from source files. Defaults to 0</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_NO_CACHE</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>WebDyne should send no-cache HTTP headers. Set to 0 to not send such headers. Defaults to 1</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_DELAYED_BLOCK_RENDER</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>By default WebDyne will render blocks targeted by a render_block() call, even those that are outside the originating <tag>&lt;perl&gt;..&lt;/perl&gt;</tag> section that
              made the call. Set to 0 to not render such blocks. Defaults to 1</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_WARNINGS_FATAL</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If a programs issues a warning via warn() this constant determines if it will be treated as a fatal error. Default is 0 (warnings not fatal). Set to 1 if you want any
              warn() to behave as if die() had been called..</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CGI_DISABLE_UPLOADS</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Disable CGI::Simple file uploads. Defaults to 1 (true - do not allow uploads).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_CGI_POST_MAX</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Maximum size of a POST request. Defaults to 512Kb</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_JSON_CANONICAL</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set is JSON encoding should be canonical, i.e. respect the order of supplied data (slightly slows down encoding). Defaults to 1 (true - preserve variable order)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_TEXT</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Display simplified errors in plain text rather than using HTML. Useful in internal WebDyne development only. By default this is 0 =&gt; the HTML error handler will be
              used.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_SHOW</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Display the error message. Only applicable in the HTML error handler</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_SHOW</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Display a fragment of the <filename>.psp</filename> source file around where the error occurred to give some context of where the error happened. Set to 0 to not display
              context.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_LINES_PRE</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Number of lines of the source file before the error occurred to display. Defaults to 4</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_LINES_POST</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Number of lines of the source file after the error occurred to display. Defaults to 4</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_SOURCE_CONTEXT_LINE_FRAGMENT_MAX</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Max line length to show. Defaults to 80 characters.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_BACKTRACE_SHOW</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show a backtrace of modules through which the error propagated. On by default, set to 0 to disable,</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_ERROR_BACKTRACE_SHORT</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove WebDyne internal modules from backtrace. Off by default, set to 1 to enable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_AUTOLOAD_POLLUTE</varname></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a method is called from a <tag>&lt;perl&gt;</tag> routine the WebDyne <methodname>AUTOLOAD</methodname> method must search multiple modules for the method owner.
              Setting this flag to 1 will pollute the WebDyne name space with the method name so that <methodname>AUTOLOAD</methodname> is not called if that method is used again (for the
              duration of the Perl process, not just that call to the page). This is dangerous and can cause confusion if different modules use the same name. In very strictly controlled
              environments - and even then only in some cases - it can result is faster throughput. Off by default, set to 1 to enable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Extension modules (e.g., WebDyne::Session) have their own constants - see each package for details.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne Directives</title>
      </info>

      <para>A limited number of directives are are available which change the way WebDyne processes pages. Directives are set in either the Apache .conf files and can be set differently per
      location. At this stage only one directive applies to the core WebDyne module:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>WebDyneHandler</varname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the handler that WebDyne should invoke instead of handling the page internally. The only other handler available today is WebDyne::Chain.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>This directive exists primarily to allow PSGI to invoke WebDyne::Chain as the primary handler. It can be used in Apache httpd.conf files, but is not very efficient:</para>

      <para><programlisting>
#  This will work, but is not very efficient
#
&lt;location /shop/&gt;
PerlHandler     WebDyne
PerlSetVar      WebDyneHandler               'WebDyne::Chain'
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain                 'WebDyne::Session'
&lt;/location&gt;


#  This is the same, and is more efficient
#
&lt;location /shop/&gt;
PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain                 'WebDyne::Session'
&lt;/location&gt;


</programlisting></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Command Line Utilities</title>
      </info>

      <para>Command line utilities are fairly basic at this stage. Installation location will vary depening on your distribution - most will default to <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>, but
      may be installed elsewhere in some cases, especially if you have nominated a <option>PREFIX</option> option when using CPAN.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>wdapacheinit</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Runs the WebDyne initialization routines, which create needed directories, modify and create Apache .conf files etc.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>wdcompile</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Usage: <command>wdcompile filename.psp</command>. Will compile a .psp file and use Data::Dumper to display the WebDyne internal representation of the page tree structure.
            Useful as a troubleshooting tool to see how HTML::TreeBuilder has parsed your source file, and to show up any misplaced tags etc.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>wdrender</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Usage: <command>wdrender filename.psp</command>. Will attempt to render the source file to screen using WebDyne. Can only do basic tasks - any advanced use (such as calls to
            the Apache request object) will fail.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>wddump</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Usage: <command>wddump filename</command>. Where filename is a compiled WebDyne source file (usually in /var/webdyne/cache). Will dump out the saved data structure of the
            compiled file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>wddebug</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Usage: <command>wddebug --status|--enable|--disable</command>. Enable/disable debugging in the WebDyne code.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>webdyne.psgi</command></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Used to run WebDyne as a PSGI process- usually invoked by Plack via plackup or starman, but can be run directly for development purposes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>wdlint</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run perl -c -w over code in __PERL__ sections on any .psp file to check for syntax errors.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Other files referenced by WebDyne</title>
      </info>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>/etc/webdyne.conf.pl</filename></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Used for storage of local constants that override WebDyne defaults. See the <link linkend="webdyne_constants">WebDyne::Constant</link> section for details</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Extending WebDyne</title>
    </info>

    <para>WebDyne can be extended by the installation and use of supplementary Perl packages. There are several standard packages that come with the Webdyne distribution, or you can build your
    own using one of the standard packages as a template.</para>

    <para>The following gives an overview of the standard packages included in the distribution, or downloadable as extensions from CPAN.</para>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title xml:id="webdyne_chain">WebDyne::Chain</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne::Chain is a module that will cascade a WebDyne request through one or more modules before delivery to the WebDyne engine. Most modules that extend WebDyne rely on
      WebDyne::Chain to get themselves inserted into the request lifecycle.</para>

      <para>Whilst WebDyne::Chain does not modify content itself, it allows any of the modules below to intercept the request as if they had been loaded by the target page directly (i.e.,
      loaded in the __PERL__ section of a page via the "use" or "require" functions).</para>

      <para>Using WebDyne::Chain you can modify the behaviour of WebDyne pages based on their location. The WebDyne::Template module can be used in such scenario to wrap all pages in a
      location with a particular template. Another would be to make all pages in a particular location static without loading the WebDyne::Static module in each page:<programlisting>&lt;Location /static&gt;

#  All pages in this location will be generated once only.
PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Static'

&lt;/Location&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para>Multiple modules can be chained at once:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;Location /&gt;

#  We want templating and session cookies for all pages on our site.
PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Session WebDyne::Template'
PerlSetVar      WebDyneTemplate '/path/to/template.psp'

&lt;/Location&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The above example would place all pages within the named template, and make session information to all pages via $self-&gt;session_id(). A good start to a rudimentary CMS.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>WebDyneChain</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Directive. Supply a space separated string of WebDyne modules that the request should be passed through.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne::Static</title>
      </info>

      <para>Loading WebDyne::Static into a __PERL__ block flags to WebDyne that the entire page should be rendered once at compile time, then the static HTML resulting from that compile will
      be handed out on subsequent requests. Any active element or code in the page will only be run once. There are no API methods associated with this module</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="static_sections">Static Sections</link> reference for more information on how to use this module within an individual page.</para>

      <para>WebDyne::Static can also be used in conjunction with the <link linkend="webdyne_chain">WebDyne::Chain</link> module to flag all files in a directory or location as static. An
      example httpd.conf snippet:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;Location /static/&gt;

PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Static'

&lt;/Location&gt;
</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne::Cache</title>
      </info>

      <para>Loading WebDyne::Cache into a __PERL__ block flags to WebDyne that the page wants the engine to call a designated routine every time it is run. The called routine can generate a
      new UID (Unique ID) for the page, or force it to be recompiled. There are no API methods associated with this module.</para>

      <para>See the <link linkend="caching_section">Caching</link> section above for more information on how to use this module with an individual page.</para>

      <para>WebDyne::Cache can also be used in conjunction with the <link linkend="webdyne_chain">WebDyne::Chain</link> module to flag all files in a particular location are subject to a cache
      handling routine. An example httpd.conf snippet:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;Location /cache/&gt;

#  Run all requests through the MyModule::cache function to see if a page should
#  be recompiled before sending it out
#
PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Cache'
PerlSetVar      WebDyneCacheHandler '&amp;MyModule::cache'

&lt;/Location&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>Note that any package used as the WebDyneCacheHandler target should be already loaded via "PerlRequire" or similar mechanism.</para>

      <para>As an example of why this could be useful consider the <link linkend="caching_section">caching examples</link> above. Instead of flagging that an individual file should only be
      re-compiled every x seconds, that policy could be applied to a whole directory with no alteration to the individual pages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne::Session</title>
      </info>

      <para>WebDyne::Session generates a unique session ID for each browser connection and stores it in a cookie. It has the following API:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>session_id()</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Function. Returns the unique session id assigned to the browser. Call via $self-&gt;session_id() from perl code.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>$WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME </varname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Constant. Holds the name of the cookie that will be used to assign the session id in the users browser. Defaults to "session". Set as per <link
            linkend="webdyne_constants">WebDyne::Constants</link> section. Resides in the <classname>WebDyne::Session::Constant</classname> package namespace.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>WebDyne Session module</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting><xi:include href="example/session1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting></para>

        <para><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/session1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>WebDyne::Session can also be used in conjunction with the <link linkend="webdyne_chain">WebDyne::Chain</link> module to make session information available to all pages within a
      location. An example httpd.conf snippet:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;Location /&gt;

# We want session cookies for our whole site
#
PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Session'

#  Change cookie name from "session" to "gingernut" for something different
#
PerlSetVar      WEBDYNE_SESSION_ID_COOKIE_NAME    'gingernut'

&lt;/Location&gt;
</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
        <title>WebDyne::Template</title>
      </info>

      <para>One of the more powerful WebDyne extensions. WebDyne::Template can be used to build CMS (Content Management Systems). It will extract the &lt;head&gt; and &lt;body&gt; sections
      from an existing HTML or WebDyne page and insert them into the corresponding head and body blocks of a template file.</para>

      <para>The merging is done once at compile time - there are no repeated search and replace operations each time the file is loaded, or server side includes, so the resulting pages are
      quite fast.</para>

      <para>Both the template and content files should be complete - there is no need to write the content without a <tag>&lt;head&gt;</tag> section, or leave out <tag>&lt;html&gt;</tag> tags.
      As a result both the content and template files can be viewed as standalone documents.</para>

      <para>The API:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><methodname>template ( filename )</methodname></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Function. Set the file name of the template to be used. If no path is specified file name will be relative to the current request directory</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>WebDyneTemplate</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Directive. Can be used to supply the template file name in a Apache Dir_Config section, or a the WEBDYNE_DIR_CONFIG section of a webdyne.conf.pl file for PSGI</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <para>The template:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Template example</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting language="html"><xi:include href="example/template1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting></para>

        <para><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/template1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>The content, run to view resulting merge:</para>

      <example>
        <info>
          <title>Template content</title>
        </info>

        <para><programlisting><xi:include href="example/template_content1.psp" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting></para>

        <para><link xlink:href="https://demo.webdyne.org/example/template_content1.psp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Run</link></para>
      </example>

      <para>In real life it is not desirable to put the template name into every content file (as was done in the above example), nor would we want to have to "use WebDyne::Template" in every
      content file.</para>

      <para>To overcome this WebDyne::Template can read the template file name using the Apache dir_config function, and assign a template on a per location basis using the WebDyneTemplate
      directive. Here is a sample <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;Location /&gt;

PerlHandler     WebDyne::Chain
PerlSetVar      WebDyneChain    'WebDyne::Template'
PerlSetVar      WebDyneTemplate '/path/to/template.psp'

&lt;/Location&gt;

</programlisting></para>

      <para>Alternatively in a PSGI environment you can create a .webdyne.conf.pl file in the directory with the template directives as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>$_={
    'WebDyne::Constant' =&gt; {
        WEBDYNE_DIR_CONFIG =&gt; {
            '' =&gt; {
                'WebDyneHandler'    =&gt; 'WebDyne::Chain',
                'WebDyneChain'      =&gt; 'WebDyne::Template',
                'WebDyneTemplate'   =&gt; 'template.psp'
            },
        },
    }
}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Credits</title>
    </info>

    <para>WebDyne relies heavily on modules and code developed and open-sourced by other authors. Without Perl, and Perl modules such as mod_perl/PSGI, HTML::Tiny, HTML::TreeBuilder, Storable
    and many other, WebDyne would not be possible. To the authors of those modules - and all the other modules used to a lesser extent by WebDyne - I convey my thanks.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    </info>

    <para>Things to note or information not otherwise contained elsewhere</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>How to check syntax on a PSP file</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>To check the syntax of a PSP file, specifically any Perl code in the __PERL__ section make sure you have a #!perl shebang after the __PERL__ delimiter as here:</para>

          <programlisting language="html">&lt;start_html&gt;
Hello World &lt;? server_time() ?&gt;
__PERL__
#!perl

sub server_time {
    my 2==1; #Error here
}</programlisting>

          <para>Then run the command <command>perl -x -c -w &lt;filename.psp&gt;</command>. This will check the file for syntax error and report back:</para>

          <screen>$ perl -c -w -x check.psp 
syntax error at check.psp line 4, near "my 2"
check.psp had compilation errors.</screen>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>How to pass $self ref if using processing instructions</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use the processing instruction form of calling a perl method it will not pass the WebDyne object ref through to your perl code. You can pass it by supplying @_ as a
          param, or just shift() and your parameters:</para>

          <programlisting language="html">&lt;start_html&gt;
Hello World &lt;? server_time(@_) ?&gt;
Hello World &lt;? server_time(shift(), 'UTC' ?&gt;
Hello World &lt;perl handler="server_time" param="UTC"/&gt;
__PERL__

sub server_time {
    #  Now we can get self ref
    my ($self, $timezone)=@_;
    #  Do something and return
}</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use of hash characters for comments in .psp files</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any # characters at the very start of a PSP file before a &lt;html&gt; or &lt;start_html&gt; tag are treated as comments and discarded - they will not be stored or displayed
          (they are <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> translated into HTML comments). This allows easy to read comments at the start of .psp files. Any # characters after the first valid
          tag are not treated specially - they will be rendered as normal HTML:</para>

          <programlisting language="html">#  This is my server time display file
#  
#  VERSION=1.23
#
&lt;start_html&gt;
Server local time is: &lt;? localtime ?&gt;</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>The &lt;checkbox&gt; tag will always set a hidden form field</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <tag>&lt;checkbox&gt;</tag> tag is unusual in that it adds a hidden field (with the same name as the checkbox) to the HTML page to retain state. Thus if you are examining
          the checkbox parameter from CGI via <varname>$_{'checkbox_name'}</varname> or <code>$self-&gt;CGI-&gt;param('checkbox_name')</code> you may get an array rather than a single value.
          The value of the checkbox (boolean, checked or unchecked, i.e. 1 or 0) will always be the first value returned. So the code <code>if ($_{'checkbox_name'}) { .. do_something }</code>
          will work as expected - but just be careful if using in an array context.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Legal Information - Licensing and Copyright</title>
    </info>

    <para>WebDyne is Copyright © Andrew Speer 2006-2025. WebDyne is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the same terms as Perl itself.</para>

    <para>WebDyne is written in Perl and uses modules from <link xlink:href="http://www.cpan.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CPAN</link> (the Comprehensive Perl Archive
    Network). CPAN modules are Copyright © the owner/author, and are available in source form by downloading from CPAN directly. All CPAN modules used are covered by the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.perl.com/pub/a/language/misc/Artistic.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Perl Artistic License</link></para>
  </section>
</article>
